Open Source Software in Practice (CS4387)

Purpose of Course

This course is a seminar designed to give upper-level students experience in programming as a collaborative practice. We do this by having students engage with open-source software by reading open issues, evaluating code, and programming working fixes. The course will progress through the skills needed to contribute to open source software development. 

Specifically we will:
1. Reinforce our knowledge of version control (Git), including how to use it in practice, why we use version control, and how it works.
2. Learn how to read open source code and find open issues.
3. Practice building code from source so we can make changes to the source code to fix issues.
4. Fix issues in open-source software

Along with learning the skills listed above, this course enables students to build their github profiles, a key requirement for showing programming aptitude to potential employers and collaborators.

(Draft) Class Schedule

Class will follow a familiar schedule (all times approximate)
- 830am–840am: attendance, “how are you”
- 845am–915am: Check in on progress for the week
- 915am–945am: Lecture (if applicable)
- 945am–10am: Break
- 10am–1130am: Work time, send bugs to the screen for class debugging

Schedule (see grid)

Weekly Grid: Open Source Software in Practice (CS4387)

Grading Policies
The course will be graded heavily on participation. I expect you to be committing meaningful code every week. 

You will be assigned three grades during the course:
1. A short essay (1200 words) where you analyze a codebase and suggest an issue to fix (25pts)
2. Your first fix (as a group), where you present a fixed issue (30pts)
3. A portfolio of fixes that makes up your total body of work for the class (45pts).

The grades above will be multiplied by the percent of weeks you commit meaningful code. I will give you 2 grace weeks, so it will be:
 # weeks making commits / 12 weeks * (sum of total points for the class).

Bennington College CS Department Class Guidelines:

1. This course outline is subject to arbitrary change. I shall announce any changes in class; if you are not present, you are still responsible for finding out what I announce.
2. Late exercises or assignments will not be accepted without an acceptable medical or compassionate reason. Exercises or assignments are due according to deadlines articulated in class.
3. You must attend classes regularly and on-time. Penalties for unexcused absences and for lateness will factor into the class grade. 
Three unexcused absences are grounds for a marginal pass, and four are grounds for failure, even if all your other work is good. Excused absences do not count towards these totals. Each tardy will be considered ½ of an absence.
4. The use of notebook computers or mobile devices is not permitted during class, except as explicitly allowed by the professor to do work directly related to some activity in class. You are expected to use analogue technologies (e.g., pencil and paper) to take notes, unless you have a special dispensation to use digital devices in class.
5. The use of artificial intelligence in coursework is not permitted, except as explicitly allowed by the professor. You must fully cite your use of artificial intelligence if you use it.
6. Office hours are first-come-first-serve, unless you have an appointment. If you request an appointment by email, please send me a selection of several times you are available.
7. Please be aware of the college policies on class attendance, as well as academic and artistic ethics. You must declare any work you submit that is generated in part or whole by AI.